Military Order of the World Wars (Central Texas Chapter) records, Inclusive: 1986-1991, undated, Bulk: 1988
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Military Order of the World Wars (Central Texas Chapter) records
Inclusive: 1986-1991, undated, Bulk: 1988
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
2923
Military Order of the World Wars
1 document box
The Military Order of the World Wars (Central Texas Chapter) records contain a variety of materials dealing with the compilation of records of servicemen from Central Texas who gave their lives in conflicts from 1917-1975.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Poor.
Biography/Profile
The Military Order of the World Wars, also known as MOWW, was established in 1919 by General John J. Pershing as a fraternity for veteran officers of the First World War. Since its inception, the MOWW has grown to include American officers of many different conflicts, including World War II, Korea, and Vietnam. The organization has a preamble and a motto, "It is nobler to serve than to be served." The MOWW fosters national security, military service, and patriotism through partnerships with the Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC), Junior Reserve Officer Training Corps (JROTC), Girl Scouts of the United States of America, Boy Scouts of America, and other organizations.
Efforts to establish the Central Texas Chapter of the MOWW began in 1986 in Austin, Texas, by Colonel Lawson W. Magruder. Their members included representatives from Bell, Bosque, Falls, Hill, Lampasas, Limestone, McLennan, and Milam counties. Perhaps the most famous action of the Central Texas Chapter of the MOWW was their compilation of the names of servicemen from these counties who gave their lives in World Wars I and II, the Korean War, and the Vietnam War. They printed and bound several copies of the Military Memorial Roll Call for the Citizens of Central Texas, 1917-1975, donating copies to libraries around central Texas, including Baylor University.
Scope and Content
The Military Order of the World Wars (Central Texas Chapter) records contain materials from 1986-1991 with some undated items. The records largely reflect the efforts of the club to compile a list of soldiers who were killed in action in conflicts from 1917-1975 who were from Central Texas.
Series I, Administrative Files, contains correspondence, rosters, and applications. Series II, Subject Files, contains lists, roll calls, and letters pertaining to the roll call project. Series III, Publicity/Press, contains letters of praise, newspaper clippings, and photographs.
Arrangement
The collection came to us in two donations. Within each donation there were folders listing the specific counties the materials related to. For the current round of processing, materials were grouped topically and the counties from each donation that were the same were merged together.
The collection includes three series: I. Administrative Files, II. Subject Files, and III. Publicity/Press.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 2923. Acquired 1989-08-11
Related Resources
Related references
Chamberlin, Charles S., "Commander-in-Chief Welcome." The Military Order of the World Wars. Accessed February 26, 2020.
Index Terms
Places
Bell County (Tex.) -- History.; Bosque County (Tex.) -- History.; Falls County (Tex.) -- History.; Hill County (Tex.) -- History.; Lampasas County (Tex.) -- History.; Limestone County (Tex.) -- History.; McLennan County (Tex.) -- History.; Milam County (Tex.) -- History.; Texas -- History -- 20th century.
Subjects
Korean War, 1950-1953; Men -- Texas -- Waco -- Societies and clubs.; Veterans -- Texas.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States.; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genres
Military records.; Photographs.; Records (Documents)
- Administrative Files, 1986-1990, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Poor.
  Biography/Profile
  The series contains correspondence, applications, and some preliminary press. The series is in poor condition.
  - Initial Actions to Establish the Chapter, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bell, Bosque, and Coryell County Records, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Falls County Records, 1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hill, Lampasas, and Limestone County Records, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - McLennan and Milam County Records, 1988-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Subject Files, 1986-1990, undated; 2
  The series contains lists, research, roll calls, and purchase requests relating to the roll call project that the club was trying to publish. The series is in poor condition.
  - Lists of World War I Dead, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lists of World War II Dead, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lists of Korea and Vietnam Dead, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Work on Compiling Roll Call, 1986-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Editions of the Roll Call, 1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Roll Call Order Forms, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Publicity/Press, 1988-1991, undated; 3
  General condition: Average.
  The series contains letters, photographs, and newspaper clippings. The series is in average condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Letters of Praise, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1988-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)